Guide to the Office of the President records, 1795-2007 RG0002
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Office of the President records
1795-2017
1821-2017
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
George Washington University. Office of the President
Trachtenberg, Stephen Joel
Elliott, Lloyd H.
Staughton, William
Samson, G. W. (George Whitefield)
Welling, James Clarke
Needham, Charles Willis
Collier, William Miller
Marvin, Cloyd Heck
Carroll, Thomas Henry
Stockton, Charles H., 1845-1924
Bacon, Joel Smith, 1802-1869
Binney, J. G. (Joseph Getchell), 1807-1877
Chapin, Stephen, 1778-1845
RG0002
339 Linear Feet 205 record center cartons, 59 document boxes, 3 slim document boxes, 4 oversize volumes, 2 oversize flat files
Although governed by a Board of Trustees, the president of the university has always been the chief administrative officer for the institution. The collection contains a mixture of personal and family papers, biographical research, and administrative records representing all but one GW President (Howard Lincoln Hodgkins, who served as president ad interim from 1921 to 1923). In addition, it contains a series of scrapbooks containing news clippings maintained by the office of the president during the early-to-mid-20th century, as well as copies of the president's annual reports (1888-1917, 1964-2007).
Collection Organization
Organized in 8 series: 1 containing materials for all presidents prior to 1927, 1 each for records from the Marvin, Colclough/Carroll, Elliott, Trachtenberg, and Knapp presidencies, 1 containing scrapbooks created by the office of the president, and 1 containing copies of the annual reports of the president.
Within the first series, the materials are organized in one sub-series for each president. Within the series for individual presidents, the materials are organized in sub-series that represent sets of files as they were transferred to the archives.
Historical Note
Although governed by a Board of Trustees, the president of the university has always been the chief administrative officer for the institution. Since the founding of Columbian College in 1821, 19 different men have served as its president. With the exception of the period between October 1841 and October 1843, there has always been an acting, interim, or regular president.
Throughout much of the 19th century, the role of the president was envisioned primarily as that of a leader among the faculty, rather than an administrator separate from it. Though charged by the Rules of the College with the "general superintendence of the government and reputation of the College," the president was also a key member of the teaching faculty, serving as their voice to the trustees and performing other duties as assigned to him by the trustees.
In keeping with the beliefs of Columbian College's founders, early supporters, and many of its trustees, six of the institution's first seven presidents were also Baptist ministers, Welling being the first exception (Greene, who followed Welling as acting president, was the last Baptist minister to serve).
With the transition from Columbian College to Columbian University in 1873 and ultimately to the George Washington University in 1904, the role of the president also shifted. Over the course of the administrations of Welling, Whitman, and Needham, the position of president was professionalized and secularized. By the early 20th century, presidents were no longer teaching a significant proportion of the unviersity's courses, and their roles were solidified as modern administrators.
Biographical and historical notes relevant to individual presidents are included in the series and subseries descriptions below.
Presidents of George Washington University
William Staughton, 1821-1827
Stephen Chapin, 1828-1841
Joel Smith Bacon, 1843-1854
Joseph Getchell Binney, 1855-1858
George Whitefield Samson, 1859-1871
James Clarke Welling, 1871-1894
Samuel Harrison Greene, acting, 1894-1895
Benaiah L. Whitman, 1895-1900
Samuel Harrison Greene, acting, 1900-1902
Charles Willis Needham, 1902-1910
Charles Herbert Stockton, 1910-1918
William Miller Collier, 1918-1921
Howard L. Hodgkins, ad interim, 1921-1923
William Mather Lewis, 1923-1927
Cloyd Heck Marvin, 1927-1959
Oswald Symister Colclough, Acting, 1959-1961
Thomas Henry Carroll, 1961-1964
Oswald Symister Colclough, acting, 1964-1965
Lloyd Hartman Elliott, 1965-1988
Stephen Joel Trachtenberg, 1988-2007
Steven Knapp, 2007-2017
Thomas J. LeBlanc, 2017-2021
Mark S. Wrighton, 2022-Present
Collection Scope and Content
The collection contains a mixture of personal and family papers, biographical research, and administrative records representing all but one GW President (Howard Lincoln Hodgkins, who served as president ad interim from 1921 to 1923). In addition, it contains a series of scrapbooks containing news clippings maintained by the office of the president during the early-to-mid-20th century, as well as copies of the president's annual reports (1888-1917, 1964-2007).
For the earlier presidents, the materials tend to be scarce and randomly collected, but as time progresses, the records become more standardized, organized and complete. No significant body of records from President Knapp has been included in this collection yet.
See the scope and content notes for the individual series and sub-series listed below for more details on what types of materials are included from each administration.
Acquisition Information
Much of this collection was transferred to the library directly from the office of the president, while other portions were gathered together by librarians, archivists, curators and university historians who were charged with tending the university's historical record throughout the 20th century. Whenever the immediate source of aquisition for a set of records is known, it is annotated at the series or sub-series level.
Restrictions on Access
Non-public materials in this collection are closed for 50 years from the date of creation. Currently, this includes portions of the Elliott and Trachtenberg series. See notes at the start of these series for assistance in identifying restricted portions of the collection.
Permission to use restricted materials may be obtained from the office of the president; please contact archives@gwu.edu to facilitate permission.
Collection note
No boxes 97-99, 137, or 254-256. 257-260 are unboxed oversize volumes.
Related Materials
Photographs of the presidents and photographs of their painted portraits, as well as a set of photo files from the Elliott administration may be found in the University Photographs Collection. Gifts and awards given to presidents Elliott and Trachtenberg may be found in the University Artifacts and Memorabilia collection. Oral histories conducted with Presidents Elliot and Trachtenberg, as well as interviews with people including Elmer Louis Kayser about the Marvin administration may be found in the Oral History collection.
Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); Students; Washington (D.C.); Scrapbooks; Education, Higher -- United States; Inaugurations; Faculty; Fund raising; Correspondence; Accreditation (Education); Planning; George Washington University--Alumni and alumnae; Knapp, Steven, 1951-
- Presidents before 1927, 1795-1975, 2003; circa 1821-1927; Series 1; 6.25 Linear Feet 12 document boxes, 1 slim document box
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is open for use.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in 10 sub-series, one for each president prior to Cloyd Heck Marvin, except for Howard Lincoln Hodgkins, for whom the archives does not hold any presidential records, and Green and Whitman, who share a sub-series due to the small quantity of their materials. The sub-series are arranged chronologically by the dataes of the presidents' administrations.
  Biographical / Historical
  In its first 126 years of existence, the institution that evolved from Columbian College to Columbian University and finally to the George Washington University was led by 13 different men who served as president or interim president: William Staughton (president 1821-1827), Stephen Chapin (president 1828-1841), Joel Smith Bacon (president 1843-1854; there was no president from October 1841 to October 1843), Joseph Getchell Binney (president 1855-1858), George W. Samson (president 1859-1871), James C. Welling (1871-1894), Samuel Harrison Greene (acting president 1894-1895 and again 1900-1902), Benaiah Longley Whitman (president 1895-1900), Charles Willis Needham (president 1902-1910), Charles Herbert Stockton (president 1910-1918), William Miller Collier (president 1918-1921), Howard Lincoln Hodgkins (interim president 1921-1923), and William Mather Lewis (president 1923-1927).
  For more information on the biographies and presidencies of each of these men, see the notes attached to each sub-series, below.
  Related Materials
  A small amount of incoming correspondence to Howard Lincoln Hodgkins, unrelated to her time as president, is located in MS2132.
  Scope and Contents
  For most of the early presidents, this series includes only scant and fairly random documentation. With the exception of the Collier and Lewis sub-series, these materials were generally collected and organized long after the presidency in question, usually by the university historian, Elmer Louis Kayser, or a librarian or archivist. Most of the materials in this series date from the time of the presidencies with which they are associated, although the series also includes general biographical information about the presidents and, in the case of Samson, also includes some family papers that were donated to the university.
  See notes at the start of each sub-series, below, for more detailed information about their contents.
  This series does not include any records from Howard Lincoln Hodgkins, who served as President Ad Interim from 1921 to 1923.
  - William Staughton collection, 1795-1829, and undated; Series 1 Sub-series 1; 0.5 Linear Feet 1 document box
    Existence and Location of Copies
    This subseries has been scanned and is available online.
    The correspondence in this sub-series is arranged chronologically; the remainder of the sub-series does not appear to follow any particular arrangement, although similar materials are grouped together.
    William Staughton (Stoughton) (1770-1829) -- a respected Baptist clergyman, educator, and music composer -- was the first president (1821-1827) of Columbian College (later George Washington University). He was born to Sutton and Keziah Staughton on January 4, 1770 in Conventry, Warwickshire, England. He attended and graduated from Bristol Baptist College in 1792. In 1793 when Dr. John Ryland became president of Bristol Baptist College, William Staughton was offered Ryland's former church at Northampton. William Staughton, however, elected to emigrate to the United States. In the fall of 1793 he arrived in Charleston, South Carolina and shortly thereafter married Maria Hanson. For the next year and a half, he preached in Georgetown, South Carolina. During the summer of 1795 he moved to New York city and subsequently settled in Bordentown, New Jersey. While residing in Bordentown, he pastored the Baptist church, headed an academy, and was ordained a Baptist minister on June 17, 1797. Between 1797 and 1805, William Staughton served as pastor at Burlington, New Jersey. In 1801, he received a Doctor of Divinity degree from Princeton. In 1805 he was offered and accepted the pastorship of the First Baptist Church in Philadelphia, a position which he held until the formation of the Sansom Street Church in 1811. In addition to his pastorate of the Sansom Street Church from 1811 until his resignation in 1822, William Staughton was the designated tutor of the Baptist Education Society of America of the Middle States founded in 1812, founder of the Philadelphia Bible Society (the first female biblical association in the world), an organizer and "corresponding secretary" of the Triennial Convention (Baptist General Convention for Missionary Purposes) from 1814 until 1826, and the principal of the theological department of the Triennial Convention in 1817. At this point, Reverand Luther Rice, a philanthropist and Baptist missionary who had returned from India, began advocating the establishment of an educational institution (college) in Washington, D. C. for training Baptist ministers. William Staughton supported Rice's idea of an educational institution. In 1819 Luther Rice and his associates founded an association, and later a tract of land was purchased on the outskirts of Washington, D. C. to be held by the convention and used for an educational facility. Two years later, the Congress of the United States granted a charter which established the Columbian College. In 1821 William Staughton was chosen to be president of Columbian College, and, on January 9, 1822, he formally opened the college. William Staughton was responsible for teaching courses in both the theological and classical departments of the college. His courses were "General History, Belles Lettres, Rhetoric, Moral Philosophy and Divinity and Pulpit Eloquence". In January 1823, William Staughton's wife died, and the students at the college wore black armbands for a month in memory of her. Four years later, William Staughton resigned as president of Columbian College because of the college's financial difficulties and differences of opinion among its trustees redgarding the theological and classical departments. During his presidency of Columbian College, he also served as chaplain to Congress during two sessions. In September 1829, William Staughton was chosen to be president of the Literary and Theological Institution (Georgetown College) in Georgetown, Scott County, Kentucky. While enroute to his new position, William Staughton died in Washington, D. C. on December 12, 1829. He was buried in the District of Columbia's Episcopal cemetery. Approximately three years later, his body was exhumed, moved to Philadelphia, and reinterred in the Sansom Street Church cemetery.
    Five months prior to his death, William Staughton had married James Peale's daughter, Anna Claypoole Peale, and she lived until 1878. William Staughton was also survived by three of his four children born during his first marriage -- Leonora, Elizabeth Ann and James Martin. Leonora Staughton was wedded to Reverand Samuel W. Lynd who later authored Memoir of the Rev. William Staughton, D. D. which was published in 1834. Elizabeth Ann Staughton was the wife of Dr. John Taylor Temple who subsequently served as a member of the Board of Trustess of Columbian College from 1832 to 1835. James Martin Staughton, bearer of a medical degree from the University of Pennyslvannia (1821), was Professor of Chemistry and of Surgery in the Columbian College's Medical School from 1821 to 1829.
    William Staughton authored a "volume of Juvenile Poems" while a teenager and an occasional sermon and discourse, such as "Eulogium on Dr. Benjamin Rush", during his pastoral career. He was a regular contributor to The Latter Day Luminary. He also edited two works: The Words of Virgil.. .To Which is Added a Large Variety of Botanical, Mythological and Historical Notes and A Compendious System of Greek Grammar written by Edward Wetenhall. In addition, William Staughton was a recognized lyricist and hymnist. According to the Biographical Dictionary of American Music, he wrote "Strike the Cymbal" in 1812 to the music of an Italian tune. A number of his hymns are reportedly contained in the 1825 edition of the Baptist Hymn Book. In addition, several of Staughton's hymns reportedly appear in the 1819 and 1826 editions of Hymns compiled by John Rippon. William Staughton was also a member of the American Philosophical Society.
    The William Staughton collection consists of incoming and outgoing correspondence, either original or photocopied, a facsimile of William Staughton address at the opening of Columbian College, printed material from The Latter Day Luminary bearing William Staughtort name, either from the publication itself or from the Luther Rice Collection, a register of writings attributed to William Staughton created in 1989 from Reverand Samuel W. Lynd' a Memoir of the Rev. William Staughton, D.D., and photographs of paintings of William Staughton. The collection also contains tracings of the alleged ancestral coat-of-arms of the Staughton family, photocopied typescripts and a notebook of excerpts from Memoir of the Rev. William Staughton, D.D., a printed biographical sketch of William Staughton, and a printed engraving of William Staughton from an unknown publication. Included in the collection is other material about William Staughton and his descendents that may be of value to researchers.
    Bibliography
    The following sources were consulted during the writing of this biographical note:
    Allibone, Samuel Austin. A Critical Dictionary of English Literature and British and American Authors, Living and Deceased, from the Earliest Accounts to the Latter Half of the Nineteenth Century.
    Appleton's Cyclopaedia of American Biography.
    Cathcart, William. The Baptist Encyclopdia.
    Dictionary of American Biography.
    Lynd, Samuel W. Memoir of the Rev. William Staughton, D. D.
    The National Cyclopaedia of American Biography.
    Who Was Who In America, Historical Volume 1607-1896.
    - William Staughton, outgoing correspondence, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Letter from William Staughton to Dr. Rogers, 1795 April 25; 1
        Existence and Location of Originals
        This is a photocopy of Dr. William Staughton's original letter. The original ones are in Wright Collection.
        Typescript is also available in PDF format.
    - William Staughton, outgoing correspondence, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Letter from William Staughton to Obadiah B. Brown, 1821 July 21; 1
      - Letter from William Staughton to Elizabeth Ann Staughton, 1821 August 6; 2
      - Letter from William Staughton to Obadiah B. Brown, 1821 September 29; 3
      - Letter from William Staughton to Obadiah B. Brown, 1821 October 29; 4
      - Letter from William Staughton to Obadiah B. Brown, 1821 November 12; 5
      - Letter from William Staughton to John, 1821? November 23; 6
      - Letter from William Staughton to Obadiah B. Brown, 1821 November 23; 7
      - Letter from William Staughton to Elizabeth Ann Staughton, 1821 December 27; 8
      - Letter from William Staughton to Elizabeth Ann Staughton, 1822 January 4; 9
    - William Staughton, outgoing correspondence, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Letter from George Holcombe, James Matlack, George Cassedy, Ephraim Bateman, Samuel Swan, Lewis Condict to James Monroe, 1823 February 26; 1
        The letter was photocopied from Gideon Welles Papers (No. 19015), the Manuscript Division, Library of Congress.
      - Letter from William Staughton, Obadiah B. Brown, and Luther Rice to James Monroe, 1823 February 26; 2
      - Letter from William Staughton to Elizabeth Ann Staughton, 1823 May 13; 3
    - William Staughton, outgoing correspondence, 1826 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Letter from William Staughton to Andrew Stevenson, 1826 April 8; 1
      - Letter from William Staughton to John T. Temple, 1826 May 1; 2
      - Letter from William Staughton to Herman Lincoln, 1826 May 17; 3
      - Letter from William Staughton to John T. Temple, 1826 August 12; 4
    - William Staughton, outgoing correspondence, 1827 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Letter from William Staughton to John T. Temple, 1827 November 18; 1
    - William Staughton, outgoing correspondence, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Letter from William Staughton to M. Van Buren, 1829 March 18; 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - William Staughton, incoming correspondence, 1821-1825 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Letter from John Connell to William Staughton, 1821 April 9; 1
        This is a photocopy of the original letter, which is in Bible, N.T., Persian, 1815 -- part of the William Ruggles Collection.
      - Letter from J. Colman to William Staughton, August 13, 1821 August 13, 1821 1821 August 13; 2
      - Letter from William Ruggles to William Staughton, 1823 January 15; 3
      - Letter from Charles A. Burnett to William Staughton, 1825 June 10; 4
    - William Staughton, address delivered at opening of Columbian College, January 9, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - William Staughton, printed materials in "Latter Day Luminary" (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Letter from Luther Rice to Berry Hicks, 1817 November 12; 1
      - Letter from Luther Rice to Berry Hicks, 1818 April 13; 2
      - Obituary: the dying experience of Mrs. Staughton, 1818 April 13; 4
    - William Staughton, lectures on botany -- Notes taken by Thomas D. Eliot (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - William Staughton, register of attributed writings (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - William Staughton, photographs (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Photocopies of images contained in the university photographs collection
    - William Staughton, photographs of oil portrait by James Peale with plaque, 6 copies (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - William Staughton, photographs of oil portrait by James Peale without plaque on wall, 6 copies (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - William Staughton, photographs of Margaretta Angelica Peale's copy of Rembrandt Peale's oil portrait, 4 copies (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - William Staughton, photographs of James Peale's oil portrait before restoration, 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - William Staughton, photographs of James Peale's stipple engraving portrait, 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - William Staughton, photograph of James Peale's oil portrait after restoration (Otherwise unidentified) (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - William Staughton, Engraving from unidentified publication (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - William Staughton, locations of oil portraits on the George Washington University campus (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - William Staughton, Biograpical Sources (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - William Staughton, Selections from his Memoir by Rev. S. W. Lynd, A. M. (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Selections from Memoir of Dr. Staughton (pp. 174-179). Chapter VII: his missionary spirit - Secretary of the General Convention, and missionaries, etc., undated; 1
      - Memoir of the Rev. William Staughton, D. D., 2
      - Selections from Memoir of Dr. Staughton (pp. 237-271). Letters (Outgoing), undated; 3
      - Memoir of the Rev. William Staughton, D.D., 4
    - William Staughton, Typescripts created from memoir (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Typescript created from Memoir of the Rev. William Staughton, D.D. (p. 203). Letter from Joseph Butterworth to William Staughton, 1822 October 10; 1
      - Typescripts created from Memoir of the Rev. William Staughton, D.D. (p. 44-45). Conversation with Thomas Paine, 1822 October 10; 2
      - Typescripts created from Memoir of the Rev. William Staughton, D.D. (p. 209-210). Address to candidates, 1822 October 10; 3
      - Typescript created from Memoir of the Rev. William Staughton, D.D. (p. 291). Extract of a letter from his son, 1829 December 14; 4
      - Typescript created from Memoir of the Rev. William Staughton, D.D. (p. 162). Scope of lectures, undated; 5
      - Typescript created from Memoir of the Rev. William Staughton, D.D. (p. 300). Letter from Irah Chase, undated; 6
    - William Staughton, Elbert S. Wade's excerpts from memoir (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - William Staughton, Printed Biographical Sketch (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - William Staughton, Sansom Street Church of Phildelphia (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - William Staughton, The "Staughton Church" Plate (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - William Staughton, Ancestral Coat-of-Arms of the Staughton Family (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - William Staughton, Descendents and Relatives (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - William Staughton, Information Concerning Family Bible (Box 1, Folder 30)